In terms of samadhi
composing the mind.
So, some people say
some practitioners say that samadhi
uh comes about is is it's something
that's comes about because of passive
passivity. Like a passive observation of thoughts
Like a passive observation of thoughts
and just relaxing.
Not doing anything about anything.
Just watching the mind and the thoughts
come and go and just relaxing.
Uh uh watching the breath not focusing
on the breath trying to get something,
just watching it.
Or
do you have to make an active effort to
compose your mind?
>> Neither, really.
Because, well, the first one it's
it sounds almost like a
like a um
artificial like a privilege that comes on a kind of
like a privilege that comes on a kind of
a
safe, protected environment.
You can afford to just observe
your impulses and so on when there isn't
anything too impulsive.
But would you remain equally
would you be able amidst of a pressuring
mind overwhelming anxiety, fear panic, or
overwhelming anxiety, fear panic, or
lust?
Would you need to go to your special
meditation place, room, environment to
calm down from it? Or would you there
and then
in that very spot
remain unmoved internally?
So, that's the the kind of the slippery
slope. It's like yes, you need some
degree of artificial environment that
will prevent your senses from being
bombarded by unsuitable sight, sound,
smell, taste, touches.
So that you can begin, you know,
swimming upstream, so to speak.
But people don't know where that line
is, and then the artificial environment
just becomes basically my safe,
comfortable space where
nothing will bother me internally,
either. And then they feel justified in
And then they feel justified in
accepting such space, so to speak. And
they feel they feel safe in developing
such samadhi.
But the moment circumstance change
circumstances change, like there was no
samadhi. It was just as I said,
artificially keeping together the
preferable environment that wasn't as
disturbing. And you you can ask yourself that, like
And you you can ask yourself that, like
after your
uh you know, whatever you invested in
your meditation practice, in your
practice of samadhi,
are you now
say you find yourself amidst crowd,
noise, unpleasant people,
you're not in a position to sit down,
count your breath, feel sensations, none
of that. You have
You have no access to any of that. So,
in other words, you can't do anything
about it internally or externally,
you are in these unsuit- unfavorable
circumstances, are you now
are you now
uh
more or less overwhelmed than before you
started meditating?
So, if you have no access to your
meditation technique, no access to your
retreat place, no access to a monastery,
no access to the
uh nature free from other people,
and those things start coming up,
how bothersome is it?
Obviously, you know, a person needs to
be honest
to to um
to kind of really get to the bottom of
it. But, when the suttas describe samadhi,
But, when the suttas describe samadhi,
they always unequivocally, very clearly
say "Not being moved by sight, sound,
smell, taste, touches they used to move
you. That's what samadhi is."
Your samadhi should be
um
should be the result of you training
towards immovability in regard to things that
immovability in regard to things that
want to move you by body, speech, and
mind.
So, the more you train in that regard,
the more you make the right choices, uh
don't allow the animal to stray,
uh go too far,
the more of a right samadhi you will
have as a result.
So, in that sense, it's an indirect
development.
But, obviously, once you have enough of
that indirect development, once you have
enough of the
samadhi nimitta, to put it that way,
you can take that up directly.
It becomes an available thing that you
could attend to rightly and cultivate on
its own.
But, again, like the simile of the
chariot in the sutta says, there is no
samadhi until virtue is purified.
Your choices and actions by body and
speech are purified. That will lead to
the purification of the mind, the
samadhi, which will then lead to the purification
which will then lead to the purification
of the views.
And the same works for the right view as
well. The right view, it's not like just
some out of the blue insight just comes
from nowhere and then you start
practicing rightly.
Yes, you start practicing rightly.
Rather, you know that you're practicing
rightly when you have the right view.
But, in order to get to the right view,
you need to develop the right samadhi.
In order to develop the right samadhi in
the suttas, you need to develop the
right virtue.
In order to develop the right virtue,
you need to stop acting out of
sensuality, spilling out by body, by
speech, mentally feeling absolved from
responsibility for your sensual acts,
feeling absolved from responsibility for
your ill will, accepting partial
responsibility saying, "Yeah, yeah, I
know I shouldn't have, but you know."
Justifying it. No, there's no excuse. If
the practice of the Dharma is the goal,
the internal criteria must be anytime I
act out of any desire,
any ill will, any distraction, that's
entirely on me and that is always an
obstruction to unification of the mind, which is
to unification of the mind, which is
always an obstruction to the
purification of the views.
That's why those who train in it, they
don't have to wish for sotapatti.
It It will be the result of the right
training. >> So just to a
>> So just to a
person can be, say, just
on a retreat watching their breath and
relaxing and not getting involved in
distractions, whatever.
>> Yeah.
>> Sensual distractions.
>> And the mind calms down.
>> Yeah.
>> And there's a kind of there is a
composure there. But
>> Definitely.
>> But but then as soon as noise enters the
picture, you get a phone call from your mother
you get a phone call from your mother
complaining about something you did or
whatever, >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> your composure's gone.
>> That is not the right samadhi.
>> No.
>> And that means what you were doing
wasn't right.
>> There is no denial that
creating the favorable circumstances
will pacify the animal, will calm the
mind down.
But that's not samadhi we speak about.
That that's That's just, as I said, a a
conditional pacification
of otherwise equally wild and unwise
animal and chitta.
So everybody starts like that, but the
problem is like do you think that's the
samadhi that the Buddha was teaching in
the suttas? Or do you know that the
samadhi from the actual suttas is a lot
more than that? In which case, go on
your retreats and and and by all means
cultivate the right environment that
will not bombard you with unsuitable
things so that you have to fend them off
all the time.
But then you will at least know that
okay, this is just a stepping stone
towards the right samadhi and the right
practice and so on. But it's not going
to be born out of it magically. If I
just protect this special environment
long enough, mind will somehow magically
discover right samadhi. You know, right
samadhi comes as a result of right
training in virtue.
So you use that environment
and your retreat place and so on to
start training those right choices,
right virtue, right values
they would then
kind of
uh pertain back
to your life outside of the retreat,
outside of the special environment. You
would continue making the same choices
of non-greed
of non-lust
non-ill will
and so on.
So if your retreat is about
rewriting the values of mental choices
that spill down into verbal and physical
actions then yes, do as many retreats as
you can.
But if your retreat is about
recharging your battery so that you can
go back and enjoy the sensual life of
ill will and unrestrained mind and
everything else, then that's not a
retreat. Certainly not the one that can lead to
Certainly not the one that can lead to
actual uprooting of suffering and
understanding.
>> Because there's a I'll just say this
other I think it's a silly view that I came
I think it's a silly view that I came
across
and the idea that, you know, if you're
if you keep your environment nice and
neat, uncluttered
this is conducive to inner peace, to at
inner samadhi.
So like externally you have this
beautiful place, no everyone's nice to
you and you feel so samadhi's made by
and you feel so samadhi's made by
>> that does that mean a wealthy person who
has many servants
is uh is a jhana master? By that logic
he would make them so.
>> Exactly.
>> Cuz their house is always tidy, always
neat, always clean. Everything is always
on time.
>> And And it's so dependent on someone
comes in and and puts the cup the wrong
way in the cupboard or something. You
lose it.
>> That's what I mean. At the end of that
\ and \ practice, you ask
yourself, am I more sensitive to stuff
or less sensitive to stuff?
Am I more quick quicker to be bothered
or bother takes a long time to arrive?
>> So, I think that's a nice measure of
progress is So, you know, something that
would really bother me before, now it
happens again and I'm I'm moved
emotionally. It's
>> Well, the nice the best measure of
progress is imagine if
sense of control is completely taken
away from you.
You're no more in a position to have a
say in what your environment looks like.
You're no more in a position to say what
you will see, hear, smell, taste, or
touch. Your senses are just bombarded. I
don't know, stuck in a hospital,
immobile, paralyzed, whatever.
Uh you are no in a position to basically
tell others what to do or what not to do
or to leave you alone or not.
How would that feel?
Like when you would be entirely just
closed within yourself,
can't put the blame on the external
circumstances, and can't change them
either.
How unmoved would you be internally?
Cuz that is the goal of samadhi.
And as I said, you begin by
somewhat artificial environment that
will help you keep the precepts. But if
you think that
artificial environment and pleasant
incense and a clean room is somehow
magically purifying your mind from these
underlying tendencies of chitta,
well, you're seriously deluded,
basically. Which means you're going to
have a rude awakening when control is
taken away from you.
You know, as you get old, sick,
accidents happen,
end up in the environment that is not
suitable for your type of samadhi, i.e. samadhi
for your type of samadhi, i.e. samadhi
that depends on external circumstances
and pleasant agreeable sight, sound,
smell, taste, touch, or or at least
avoidance of the disagreeable ones,
well, then you will see how untamed your
mind actually still is.
So, yeah, you don't want to wait for
that to come.
So, it doesn't mean you need to disrupt
your environment now, but you need to
start internally, begin questioning it,
begin contemplating scenarios, what if
this environment were to change, how
affected would I be by that?
Would I still be able to maintain
whatever I think my inner composure
\ samadhi is?
Or I it just wouldn't work. It wouldn't
work. My samadhi doesn't work if there
is noise. My samadhi doesn't work if
there are other people doing this,
saying that. If I can hear sounds or you
know, if I didn't sleep enough or if I
have to work, my samadhi doesn't work.
That is not samadhi.
>> But you want to have your samadhi work
is like even if there's work, even if
there's noise, even if it's a mess
>> Anything.
>> that I inside internally
>> should be unaffected by that if it's the
right samadhi.
>> There's no internal resistance.
>> No.
>> No craving.
>> Cuz the right samadhi comes on account
of right virtue.
So, if the right virtue that purifies
the mind
at least diminishes greed, aversion,
distraction, and acting out of those
things, they will be quite a um
substantial samadhi established
as a result of that immovability.
But that cannot does not come, as I
said, out of the blue, falls from the
sky, you just suddenly have this
capacity to be unmoved.
You become unmoved by training how not
to move in regard to things that want to
move you.
And again, the suttas say that in regard
to the other hand,
the one who cannot be moved by his mind,
he's the one that moves his mind.
Um and uh, all all the other similes of
basically um,
sight, sound, smell, taste, touches,
were never the root of the problem.
They're never the root of the
disturbance. Confusing them for being so means
Confusing them for being so means
maintaining your very wrong views that
are basically they are the root, they are
basically they are the root, they are
causing
the major liability to suffering and all
the other disturbances.
>> And also they're they're not the
the uh, cure to your problem.
>> No, it won't uproot it. No, no, they
remain unchanged.
Yeah, even if you have the privilege of,
as I said, protecting and catering your
environment for the rest of your life,
sickness, aging, death will come and
that will be the destruction of your
environment, whether you want it or not.
Even if you have the most
peaceful death,
not like in some dirty hospital or
something surrounded by strangers, it's
still death. It's still the shutting
down of the senses that you still depend
upon. So, it's going to feel the same.
So, it's going to feel the same.
So, better start training in it
internally by through recognition and
contemplation of these scenarios and
then keeping a corner of your eye at the
animal, how much it moves, how much it
twitches, and conditioning it to hold on, no, this
and conditioning it to hold on, no, this
is the actual reality.
>> And let's get ready for it. Let's get
ready for
>> All you need to do is stop resisting it.
How will you know if if your dog is
resisting something or not?
By locking it inside and protecting it
and never exposing it to that, to those
ideas? No. It might remain perfectly peaceful
No. It might remain perfectly peaceful
just because you're sheltering it.
And when you're not able to shelter it,
same old beast will come up
and cause the damage and everything
else. So, yeah, you shelter it so that it
So, yeah, you shelter it so that it
doesn't escape, but then you actually
have to start
recollecting, providing these ideas in
order for it to learn how to be peaceful
within that.
Because it's possible, because as I
said, the disturbance does not come from
the circumstances, it comes from the
resistance of the chitta, but ego.
If that's fully
trained out of
the chitta,
then it's just peace. Doesn't matter
what condition you're in.
That is aranjit.